Finding Aid for Current Topic Club (Owosso, Mich.) Records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Current Topic Club (Owosso, Mich.) Records 1894-1975
Current Topic Club (Owosso, Mich.)
1.5 linear feet (in 2 boxes)
90126 Bk 2
Constitution and bylaws, correspondence, minutes, photographs, and programs; minutes describe presentation by Raoul Wallenberg about Sweden and Swedish architecture.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This record group came from the Current Topic Club, Owosso, Michigan in June 1989. 7696
No further additions to the records expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Current Topic Club of Owosso, Michigan was organized in 1893 and held its first meeting on January 8, 1894 when officers were elected and a constitution and bylaws approved. Article II of the constitution says: "The object of this club is to promote an interest in reading and a freedom in conversation by the discussion of current events." The club met each Monday afternoon at a member's home where a program prepared by one of their number was presented. Program topics were selected each spring by a committee following discussion by the full membership; topics were assigned to an individual on a rotating basis and a printed program prepared for the following club year. Members accepted their assigned topics in order to remain on the active roll. At each meeting discussion of current issues followed the formal program, usually during their refreshment time. Business matters, such as approval of an infrequent bill, were not a prominent part of the club's minutes.
Occasionally, the Current Topic Club joined with the Owosso Women's Club to sponsor a program, a reception, or a city-wide event. An example of a co-sponsored event was the highly successful city Christmas tree lighting first held in 1913 with a band, choral groups, children carolling, and church choirs; attendance was estimated at more than 3000.
The Current Topic Club was affiliated with both the Michigan State Federation of Women's Clubs and the General Federation of Women's Clubs (USA) for a number of years beginning in 1896. One of the Owosso club's members, Mrs. Josephine M. Gould, served as president of the State Federation in 1903-1904.
The club still meets, now on alternate Mondays, and the membership is preparing to mark their 100th anniversary in 1994.
The Current Topic Club records, 1894-1975 consist of 1.5 linear feet in two boxes and are organized divided into three series: Administrative Records, Photographs and Programs.
The Administrative records series includes files on the club's Constitution and Bylaws, Minutes and Correspondence. The Correspondence consists of only a few items, such as thank-you notes. The Minutes are contained in bound books, each book covering a number of years. There are only two gaps in their coverage, October 1898-April 1901, and April 1920-May 1925. The programs series includes copies of all yearly printed programs from 1897 through the 1974-1975 club year. Photographs consist of three group portraits of the Current Topic Club membership made in August 1924, summer(?) 1944--their 50th Anniversary, and May 1973. Each is labeled.
The records of the Current Topic Club are an important source of information for the researcher studying women's activities and interests, because they cover an extended time span in a well-documented manner. The records represent a significant addition to the history of women in Michigan, and also throw light on an important period in the growth of a typical mid-western city.
There were occasions when men were invited to address the group. An important example here was the appearance of Raoul Wallenberg, a student from Sweden who had just graduated from the University of Michigan College of Architecture, and delayed his return home in order to speak to the club at the invitation of Mrs. L. L. Woodard. The minutes for February 18, 1935 record that he discussed the geography and history of Sweden, described Swedish architecture and passed around sketches illustrating his points.
Musical programs and member-prepared skits were a feature of some meetings. They were interested in political events of the day and often signed petitions on pending legislative action, e.g., school taxes, child labor, county agricultural extension service, and state aid to libraries.
In the 1949-1950 club year the members devoted all meetings to women and the women's movement for the first time, and continued this theme in 1950-1951. In earlier years one meeting each year centered around a famous woman.
Subjects:
Owosso (Mich.); Wallenberg, Raoul, 1912-1947.; Women--Michigan--Owosso--Societies and clubs.
- Administrative Records
  - Constitution (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1894-1975
    - January 1894-May 1898
    - October 1901-April 1905
    - October 1905-March 1911
    - October 1911-March 1914
    - March 1914-April 1916
    - October 1916-March 1918
    - March 1918-March 1920
    - October 1926-March 1933
    - October 1933-October 1941
    - October 1941-April 1950
    - October 1950-April 1962
    - October 1962-April 1975
    - October 1975-May 1998
  - Correspondence
  - Newspaper Clippings ad Miscellaneous
- Photographs
  - Current Topic Club Group Portrait, August 25, 1924 (Box 1)
  - Current Topic Club Group Portrait, Summer 1944 (Box 1)
  - Current Topic Club Group Portrait, May 14, 1973 (Box 1)
- Programs, 1897-1975
  - Annual Files, 1897-1975, 79 folders (Box 2)
  - Programs, miscellaneous (Box 2)